Guide to the Richard W. Rychtarik / Hart Crane Papers 1923-1935 MSS.103
Fales Library and Special Collections
Richard W. Rychtarik/Hart Crane Papers
1923-1935
Fales Library and Special Collections
Crane, Hart, 1899-1932
MSS.103
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Harold Hart Crane was born in 1899 and became a significant voice within modernist American poetry of the first half of the twentieth century. Crane moved to New York City and mixed with other prominent writers of the time and was influenced by both contemporary currents in poetry, and his early affinity for nineteenth-century French poets. In 1930, Crane received some acclaim from the publication of "The Bridge," his book-length poem that depicts New York City and his outlook on America in general. In 1932, upon completing a Guggenheim fellowship in Mexico, he set off by ship back to New York, but committed suicide by jumping from the deck during his passage.
Provenance
The Richard W. Rychtarik Hart Crane Papers were the gift of the Richard W. Rychtarik Estate by Mrs. Gertrude Rychtarik. The papers were donated in September, 2000. The collection consists of letters, postcards and photographs, as well as some supplemental materials, that were kept by Mr. Rychtarik, a close personal friend of Crane.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Harold Hart Crane was born in 1899 in Garrettsville, Ohio and became a significant voice within modernist American poetry of the first half of the twentieth century. Though without a college education and dissuaded from a career in poetry, Crane moved to New York City to write, where he met other prominent writers of the time, such as E. E. Cummings, Jean Toomer and Katherine Anne Porter. He was influenced by both the contemporary currents in poetry, such as T.S. Elliot, and his early affinity for nineteenth-century French poets, like Rimbaud. Most of his published material was written between 1924 and 1926, due in some part to his bouts with drinking and problems that arose from being gay in a culture that rejected homosexuality. In 1930, Crane received acclaim and distinction from the publication of "The Bridge," his book-length poem that depicts New York City and his outlook on America in general. Crane had struggled to complete "The Bridge," and when he found himself particularly at a loss, he sought inspiration by traveling to an island near Cuba and Europe. Once awarded a Guggenheim fellowship in 1931, he temporarily settled in Mexico. In 1932, upon completing the fellowship, he set off to New York from Mexico; at the age of thirty-three, Crane committed suicide by jumping into the Gulf of Mexico from the deck of the S. S. Orizaba during his passage.
Sources:
"Hart Crane." The Academy of American Poets. 2001. [http://www.poets.org/poets].
Nelson, Cary. (Ed). "Hart Crane: Biographical Sketch." An Online Journal and Multimedia Companion to the 'Anthology of Modern American Poetry. Oxford University Press, 2000.' Department of English, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. 2002. [http://www.english.uiuc.edu/maps/poets/a_f/crane/bio.htm]
Scope and Content Note
The Papers consist of letters, postcards, photographs, drawings, tearsheets, and clippings about Crane. Most of the items are typed letters signed by Crane to Charlotte and/or Richard Rychtarik. (Richard Rychtarik was an American set and costume designer of major productions at the Metropolitan Opera and other companies.) There are two letters from Waldo Frank to Crane, a handful of letters from Grace Hart Crane, and correspondence with Philip Horton. Among the photos are images of Crane in Brooklyn with the Bridge in the background, images of his rooms, of his visit to Woodstock, NY, and signed portraits, including one signed portrait by Walker Evans.
The collection had been kept in a very acidic scrapbook which was disbound when the Fales Library received the materials. Many of the letters had been stapled to the acidic backing. These have been removed. When the backings contained information about the letters, they were retained. The scrapbook had its own numbering system, which is preserved on the folders and, often written on the letters themselves.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
The Papers are in one series, which corresponds to the arrangement of the scrapbook in which they had been housed. It is roughly chronological, though there are some photos and materials not in that order and other materials that were not a part of the original scrapbook. These follow the scrapbook order. Printed materials and related correspondence are listed at the end of the collection.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into one series.
Missing Title
Series I
Postcards.; Poets, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Poetry, Modern -- 20th century.; Drawings; American poetry -- 20th century.; Tear sheets.; Poets, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Poets -- United States.; Authors |z United States.; Horton, Philip; Frank, Waldo David, 1889-1967; Rychtarik, Richard, 1894-1982; Evans, Walker, 1903-1975; Crane, Hart, 1899-1932
- Series I:
  - Scrapbook title page, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, [March 1923] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photo of Hart Crane [1923]. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, March 30, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, [April 4, 1923] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, April 13, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, [April 23, 1923] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, Wednesday [1923]; Correspondence, Waldo Frank to Hart Crane (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Richard, [May 1923] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, May 30, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, June 5, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Richard, June 21, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, July 9, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, July 21, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, [August 19, 1923] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, [August 26, 1923] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, [August 28, 1923] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, September 23, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, October 2, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, Friday evening [1923] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, December 10, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photos of Woodstock, NY Dec-23, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, January 6, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, March 5, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, April 15, [1924] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, July 30, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, November 18, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, January 29, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, February 28, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, April 9, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, May 18, [1925] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, June 2, [1925] (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, September 15, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, [1925] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, September 26, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, October 14, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, October 22, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, December 1, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, December 14, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, March 2, [1926] (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, March 23, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, April 11, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, April 25, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, April 30, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Richard, May 4, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Photo of Hart Crane, inscribed "To Lotte and Richard with love, Hart" and text on back [August 14, 1926] (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, November 1, [1926] (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, December 31, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, July 9, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, November 29, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, March 28, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, September 16, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, October 6, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, October 23, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, December 28, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard,, February 26, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte photo, February 11, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, March 30, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Richard, April 3, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte, [ca. 1931] (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, two postcards, May 14, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, May 14, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Richard, September 24, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, September 6, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard with photos, November 4, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, Christmas 1928 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, February 8, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Photos of Hart Crane, [1932] (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard with photo with letter on back, [March 1, 1932] (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, March 20, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence, Hart Crane to Charlotte and Richard, April 20, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Photo of Hart Crane on rooftop with bridge in background, inscribed to Charlotte and Richard; Photo of unknown man, undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Photos of Hart Crane's apartment (not numbered), inscribed to Charlotte and Richard, upstate, etc., undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Clippings (xeroxed), undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Tear Sheets (xeroxed), undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Correspondence, Grace Hart Crane, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Correspondence, Philip Horton and related correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Printed materials and fascimile of a letter, undated (Box 1, Folder 79)